A Guide to the Brooks Equestrian Photograph Collection, 1932-1986
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Brooks Equestrian Photograph Collection 1932-1986
Thomas Balch Library
VC 0051
This collection contains twenty-six oversized photographs of equestrian competitions representing races at both the Charles Town Race Track and the Shenandoah Downs. Many of the items are mounted. The earliest dated photograph from 1932 was taken one year prior to West Virginia's legalization of the sport.
Linda Brooks
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Linda Brooks, Leesburg, VA
Accruals
2011.0265
Historical Information
Horseracing was a popular amusement in Charles Town, West Virginia as early as 1786, and September 1808 issue of Farmer's Repository notified the public of three horseracing events the following month. Financed by private donations and club subscription fees, the sport flourished throughout the 19th century. The Shenandoah Valley Jockey Club, the first race track in the state, opened on 2 December 1933 in Charles Town shortly after West Virginia legalized racing and betting. The first two years proved financially unsuccessful. Convinced that promoting the race track during the winter season to residents in Washington and Baltimore would yield success, Albert J. Boyle (d. 1957) invested $160,000 in the venture, rechristening the organization as the Charles Town Jockey Club. His prediction proved correct, the business thrived, and Boyle remained a prominent figure in West Virginia racing.
Seeing the financial rewards possible, a newly formed group of investors purchased property across the road to construct a second race track. The group encountered resistance from churches opposed to gambling and the Charles Town Jockey Club, which wished to maintain its monopoly. After a contentious election, voters approved the new track by a narrow margin of 357 votes. Considerable litigation resulted in a decision by the West Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals that allowed construction to continue. The new track, known as Shenandoah Downs opened in 1959. For two decades, the tracks competed for prime racing dates from the West Virginia Racing Commission. The rivalry ended in 1972 when the Shenandoah Corporation, owner of Shenandoah Downs, purchased the Charles Town Race Track. From that point forward year-round racing continued at Charles Town Rack Track while the Shenandoah Downs operated as a training track.
Scope and Content
This collection contains twenty-six oversized photographs of equestrian competitions representing races at both the Charles Town Race Track and the Shenandoah Downs. Many of the items are mounted. The earliest dated photograph from 1932 was taken one year prior to West Virginia's legalization of the sport.
Arrangement
Folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Bushong, Millard Kessler. A History of Jefferson County, West Virginia. 1941. Reprint, Bowie: Heritage Books, Inc., 2002.
Bushong, Millard Kessler. Historic Jefferson County. Boyce, VA: Carr Publishing Co., 1972.
Nations, Jeff. "Charles Town Celebrates 75 Years." The Journal, December 25, 2008. http://www.journal-news.net/page/content.detail/id/513766.html
"Shenandoah Downs," The West Virginia Encyclopedia, last modified October 29 2010, accessed February 22, 2013, http://www.wvencyclopedia.org/articles/387
Theriault, William D. "Charles Town Races," The West Virginia Encyclopedia, accessed February 22, 2013, http://www.wvencyclopedia.org/articles/1088
Other Finding Aid
Past Perfect Catalog records
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
None
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - [Unidentified Jockey on Horse] 1940-1950
  - [Unidentified Man with Horse] 1940-1950
  - [Unidentified Jockey on Horse with 5 Unidentified Men] 1940-1950
  - [Unidentified Jockey on Horse] 1932
  - Triumvirate 17 October 1939
  - Flower Battle 30 June 1943
  - Flower Battle 24 June 1944
  - Flower Battle 24 June 1944
  - Flower Battle 28 June 1944
  - Patrician 17 July 1946
  - Patrician 17 June 1946
  - French Nine 19 July 1946
  - French Nine 19 July 1946
  - French Nine 03 June 1947
  - French Nine 03 June 1948
  - Patrician 03 July 1948
  - Butler 31 May 1950
  - French Nine 02 April 1950
  - Hasty Break 22 July 1953
  - Twirl 31 July 1953
  - War Babu 31 May 1965
  - Sugar Loch 28 June 1965
  - Sugar Loch 08 September 1965
  - Sugar Loch 07 October 1965
  - Peebona 01 November 1965
  - Strawberry Hill 12 April 1986